Back to editor. Now, lets add a new "src" directory to the project.
Done. Lets try to add this directory to git using the "git add src" command.
Lets see the "git status"
Hmm, strange. No changes. Lets try "git commit"
Nothing happened.
And git is even writing that "nothing to commit, working tree clean."
What is the problem?
Thats where git behaves not as we thing it should
Due to the historical reasons git can't work with empty folders. And mostly it cant see empty directories at all.
To workaround this directory is made non-empty by putting a stub zero-sized file inside it.
its usually called ".gitkeep", so that its clear why is it needed at all. And then the directory can be added to git.
In our case we dont need this file as we are going to create a "script.js" file in our "src" directory.
Lets write some script inside. Git doesn't care what programming language is used.
In this case its javascript. Done.
And let's include this file into "index.html"
Saving the changes.
Now lets open the terminal again and type "git status".
Now the output consists of 2 parts.
Above there are changes in the files that git is tracking,
that are in the Index already. Below it shows that project has directory that git doesnt know yet.
Note, that its only showing the directory, but not the files inside it.
It is assumed that if the directory is not known to git yet, so the files inside it.
Lets add our changeset to git. For that lets use "git add ." command.
So we are giving the whole current directory to the "git add" command.
If "git add" retrieves a directory it adds all its changes to the Index.
This is very convenient if changed one file, then another, then yet another change and then just "git add ." and it adds it all.
Lets have a look at "git status".
Thats it. Both files were added to the git.
"git add ." command that we've just used is very convenient, but it has a side effect.
The problem is that the project directory may have some other files, that we dont want to add to the repository.
E.g: I've opened the project in the other editor - WebStorm.
Im not even going to do anything here. Just open the project and go back.
Note, the work directory has a new directory ".idea". It contains the Webstorms IDE files.
If we are going to execute "git add .", then we are going to add these ".idea" files together with our changes.
But IDE related files should not be in the repository. To cancel these changes,
we can use the command that git is telling us to use: "git reset HEAD .idea"
Git is going to drop changes for the ".idea" directory from the Index.
"git reset" is actually a very powerful command. It can rollback changes in many different cases.
We are going to have a look at it in more details in one of the next videos of our screencast.
To avoid this problem in future lets create a ".gitignore" file and put ".idea" there.
Now if I run "git status" we see the changes that were indexed previously.
We also see a new ".gitignore" file and see no ".idea", albeit its still there.
Just its in the ignore file and most git commands is going to completely ignore this directory.
Keep in mind that even if something is in the ignore file one can add it to git Index,
but just adding "--force" or shorter "-f" flag to the "git add" command.
It can be convenient if, for example, the file you need to add is deep inside the directory that is ignored.
And when the file is added to the Index all its changes are going to be tracked, independently of its presence in ".gitignore".
Further on we are going to work in the same way with files that were added like that. No additional flags are needed.
You can find more information on ".gitignore" in the corresponding issue of this screencast.
To give you some details on what the git Index is Im going to open the editor and put some changes to the "index.html" file,
actually Im just calling the "hello" function that is declared in the included script.
Now if you type "git status" you can see a very interesting thing.
Index as it is shown in the first part of the output has exactly the same changes that we've added previously.
That means that when we add a file to the Index,
it saved not only its name, but the whole contents. And when you run the "git commit"
the repository added it, exactly what we've added to the Index. But the changes done afterwards are in the work directory only.
In this section we list the files that has unindexed changes.
In our case we've jsut changed "index.html" and so we have it here.
And finally in the third part we have files that git is not tracking yet. ".gitignore" was not yet added to the index, therefore its here.
To make a commit including all the latest changes lets add them to the Index. Like that.
Now lets "git status".
No unindexed changes.
Ok, its time to save everything we have in the repository. To do that lets use "git commit" with "-m" flag.
"-m" allows us to write the commit comment right away, without opening the editor. Its very convenient when the message is short.
Like "fixed this issue"
Or in our case: "added script".
Executing, done. Our changes are finally saved to the repository.
And heres a new commit identifier. By it we can get the current state of the project files, that we've just saved at any time.
Now if I check "git status" we can see that its all clean, except for the ".gitignore". Lets add it to the repository. "git add .gitignore".
Here it is in the Index and "git commit -m'Add gitignore'".
Done. Now you may ask a question:"Why havent you just added '.gitignore' the previous commit? Why save it separately?"
The answer is crucial as it explains how to use git correctly.
I hope it will be clear for you after watching the next video of this screencast.